<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some prison meditations of an humble heart given forth from a child in Israel, whose soul very dearly loveth his Heavenly Fathers children : much desiring, (and travelling in spirit for) their prosperity in the truth, even as for his own soul ... / by a sufferer for the truth in the common goal of Edmondsbury, whose earthen vessel bears the name of William Bennit.</title>
            <author>Bennit, William, d. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12725044</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12725044</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66336</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66336)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1030:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some prison meditations of an humble heart given forth from a child in Israel, whose soul very dearly loveth his Heavenly Fathers children : much desiring, (and travelling in spirit for) their prosperity in the truth, even as for his own soul ... / by a sufferer for the truth in the common goal of Edmondsbury, whose earthen vessel bears the name of William Bennit.</title>
                  <author>Bennit, William, d. 1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66336:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME Priſon Meditations OF AN Humble Heart: Given forth from a Child in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> whoſe Soul very dearly loveth his Heavenly Fathers Children; much deſiring, (and travelling in ſpirit for) their proſperity, in the Truth; even as for his own ſoul; and the Author hereof, believing and knowing, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, may (if the Lord will) be of ſervice unto many; of the tender, honeſt, ſimple, ſingle, upright-hearted one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; (who are following (on to know) the Lord, in the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of righteouſneſs; and who d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſireth to paſs over on to the end; in the ſtrait way of holineſs) therfore, even for their ſakes, is this following Treatiſe publiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d from a conſtraint of Gods love; in ſingleneſs and ſimpliſity of heart.</p>
            <p>By a Sufferer for the Truth in the Common Coal of <hi>Edmondsbury,</hi> whoſe Earthen Veſſel bears the name of WILLIAM BENNIT.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66336:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66336:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Some Priſon Meditations of an humble Heart, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>OH, Oh my Soul, be not unmindful of the large mercy and goodneſs of the Lord ſhewed towards thee, neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the exceeding loving kindneſs of the Holy One manifeſted unto thee Oh my Soul; Oh let the ſence of what the Lord thy dear, tender, pittiful, compaſſionate God hath done for thee; continually be freſh in and upon thee oh my Soul, for the Lord thy God hath freely done that for thee, which none beſides him the mighty one could do: Oh my Soul the Lord hath brought thee out of the pit, even out of the horrible pit, and out of the mire and clay, wherein thou once ſtuck ſo faſt, as that thou could never have been able to have gotten out by all means poſſible thou could have invented, but muſt have ſunk deeper and deeper therein, and ſo have periſhed for ever, had not the Lord God of infinite mercy helped thee, who did caſt his eye of pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon thee, and out of his meer mercy, love and free grace, ſtretched out his hand to help thee oh my Soul, when none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him could help thee, and by his arme of loving kindneſs lifted thee up out of the horrible pit, out of the mire and clay, and hath ſet thy feet upon a Rock which ſtands ſure, and can never be moved, and thereon he eſtabliſheth thy goings, praiſes, pure living righteous Praiſes to the Lord thy God be rendered by thee Oh my Soul even for ever and for ever more.</p>
               <p>Oh my Soul remember thou waſt once even like a poor ſilly ſheep without a ſhepherd wandering upon the barren mountains and dry heaths in the wilderneſs and ſolitary places, full of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſorrow, and perplexity, and knew not the way to the fold of reſt, oftentimes mourning and weeping alone as a Dove with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her Mate, when no eye ſaw thy ſorrow but the Lord alone; often ſaying in thy heart, whoſe ſtate and condition is ſo miſerable as mine? who ſo poor and deſolate as I? none knoweth how i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66336:3"/> is with me but the Lord alone: And indeed the Lord then ſaw thee and knew how it was with thee oh my Soul, and he the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God of unfathomable bowels of compaſſion, beheld thee in that day when thou did eat thy bread weeping, and mingled thy drink with thy tears, and he the compaſſionate one heard thy ſecret crys, and knew thy ſecret deſires, and thy ſighing and groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning entered into his ears, and thy tears which thou dropped upon his altar, laid open unto the view of the eye of thy tender mercyful God, and his tender bowels was moved with pitty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, and for his own ſeed ſake he had compaſſion upon thee oh my ſoul, and helped thee in the day of thy trouble, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered thee out of diſtreſs, who freely reached forth his arme unto thee and took thee by the hand, and brought thee out of the wilderneſſes and deſolate places, and ſet thy feet in the right way which hath led thee to a City of habitation, and to the fold of reſt; and now the Lord (who both ſought thee and found thee out, and brought thee out of the wilderneſs, and from off the barren mountains) he is become thy ſhepherd oh my ſoul; and how canſt thou want any good thing, he oftentimes feedeth thee, and even cauſeth thee to lie down in green Paſtures and leadeth thee by the ſtill waters, even <hi>Shilos</hi> brook which runs ſoftly, and he ſpreadeth thy Table in the ſight of thy enemies, and anointeth thy head with the oyle of gladneſs, and cauſeth thy cup to overflow with new wine, and hath brought thee to ſit under thy own Vine, and under thy fig tree, and none ſhall make thee afraid oh my ſoul: Oh the goodneſs of the Lord, oh the kindneſs of the Lord, oh the mercy of the Lord, oh the pitty of the Lord, oh the compaſſion of the Lord God of tender bowels is even unutterable, unſpeakable, unfathomable and incomprehenſible; Oh the heighth, oh the depth, oh the length, oh the breadth of the love of the Lord: oh my ſoul! truly when thou meditateſt of the goodneſs of the Lord, and conſidereſt of his loving kindneſs and mercy ſhewed towards thee, oh how can but the ſence thereof pitch thee even upon a ſtand of admiration: Oh ſurely, ſurely when thou oh my ſoul looketh back into his works and conſidereſt how much he hath wrought in thee and for thee, thou can ſee no end of his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; oh praiſes, oh living praiſes, holy righteous praiſes unto the pure holy righteous Lord God be aſcribed by thee oh my ſoul for ever and for ever more. Oh my Soul as thou art kept in the freſh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66336:3"/> ſence and remembrance of the great loving kindneſs, the great mercy, the great pitty and unſpeakable compaſſion of the Lord thy tender God which he hath and daily doth manifeſt unto thee oh my ſoul; Oh how canſt thou but in the ſence of Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable love abound in love, in pitty, in mercy, in kindneſs, in tenderneſs and compaſſion towards all people, but eſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all ſouls, who are ſeeking, thirſting, hungring, breathing, crying and panting after Righteouſneſs, peace and everlaſting reſt, and eternal happineſs: Oh my ſoul the Lord thy God knoweth the frame of thy ſpirit, the Lord knoweth the tenderneſs of thy bowels, and the openneſs of thy boſom towards all the ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers after Righteouſneſs, towards all the travellers to Sion, and towards all the Mourners therein: Oh my ſoul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how that at ſome times when the great fountain, the great deep hath opened and iſſued forth of his fulneſs into thee oh my ſoul; and when joy hath come into thy heart as a river, and gladneſs as a mighty ſtream, refreſhings as ſhoures in the ſpring, and conſolation as due upon the tender plants, and when thou could ſing for joy of heart, and ſhout out aloud even pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and halleluiahs to thy God, that then even then thou oh my ſoul remembreth the poor and needy in his own eyes; and think'ſt thou heareſt his cry ſounding in thy ear, and his ſoul ſaying in ſecret; Oh how many is there who eateth of the largeſt loaves, &amp; drinketh of the largeſt full flagons; but oh alaſs for me, I have ſcarce a drop of refreſhment, hardly a crum of conſolation, but my tears is my m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at and drink day and night, whileſt my enemy ſaith unto me where is thy God: Oh I go bowed down all the day long, and none knoweth my ſorrow but the Lord alone; Oh I am even as an Owle in the deſart, and as the Pelican in the Wilderneſs, I am as the alone quail in the ſtuble fields, and as a Dove mourning for the loſs of her Mate, and as the alone Sparrow upon the houſe top, and as a woman forſaken and grieved in ſpirit; Oh whoſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is like mine! is there any amongſt the Sons and daughters of Men like unto me? is there any ſo poor as I? oh is there any ſo needy as I? oh is there any ſo weak and feeble as I? is there any ſo fooliſh as I? oh is there any ſo dry and barren as I? oh is there any ſo cold and fruitleſs to Godward as I? is there any ſo deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late as I? Oh my leanneſs, oh my leanneſs, oh how long, how long ſhall it be thus with me? oh how long, how long ſhall I ſit mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as by the river of <hi>Babylon</hi> with my Harp laid aſide? oh when,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66336:4"/> when ſhall I walk again in Sion, and travel in the ſtreets of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem? with a new ſong in my mouth, and everlaſting joy upon my head, and living praiſes in my heart unto the Lord who dwelleth in his Sion, and his preſence is great in his Jeruſalem? but oh alaſs for me, I am as one caſt out of his ſight, and one who walketh dejected all the day long; Oh when will the Lord cauſe the days of my mourning to be over, and the nights of my ſorrow to paſs away, and my ſighings and groanings to vaniſh, and all tears to be wiped from mine eyes; Oh when will the Lord give me beauty inſtead of aſhes, the oyle of joy for mourning, and the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs, that I (a poor dry barren one) might become a tree of Righteouſneſs, bringing forth fruit of holineſs abundantly to the praiſe of the Lord God, that he in and through me might be glorified; oh when ſhall my winter be over, and the terrible ſtorms gone; Oh when ſhall the cold nipping froſts be expelled, and the darkneſs and gloomineſs be extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed? Oh when will the Sun of Righteouſneſs break forth unto me in his glory, and his warm beams refreſh and warm my poor cold ſoul? Oh when will the ſpring come, when ſhall I know a ſpring time in the Lord? oh when will Summer come? oh when will the ſinging of birds come? oh when ſhall I hear the voice of the Turtle in my Land? oh when will the ſhoures from on high fall down upon my ſoul? oh when ſhall I receive the early and latter rain? oh when ſhall I come to ſit under my own Vine, and under my fig tree, and none to make me afraid? Oh how long ſhall my beloved be hid from me as in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lifts of the Rocks, and as in the ſecret places of the Stares? ſometimes indeed he ſhews himſelf unto me as behind the wall, and as through a lattis, and then my bowels, my tender bowels are moved for him: Oh when, oh when ſhall I have a full enjoyment of him whom my ſoul loveth; oh that I could but plainly hear his voice, and perfectly ſee his face; for oh indeed ſweet is his voice, and his countenance is very comely; oh my ſoul deſireth him in the night ſeaſon, and in the morning I ſeek him early; but oh I cannot find him whom my ſoul loveth, for he hath withdrawn himſelf from me, and that is the cauſe of my leanneſs, coldneſs, barrenneſs and unfruitfulneſs to Godward which is the cauſe of my ſorrow, tears, ſighing, groaning, mourning, and walking dejected all the day long.</p>
               <p>Oh indeed there was a time once when my beloved kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cked at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66336:4"/> the door of my heart, ſaying again and again, open, open, unto me; my head is wet with dew, and my locks filled with the drops of the night; open, open unto me and let me in; but oh wo's me I was gotten into a bed of falſe eaſe and wrong ſecurity, and was loath to come out; but I made excuſes and ſaid, I have put off my coat, how ſhall I put it on, I have waſhed my feet how ſhall I defile them, &amp;c. and I lingered ſo long as that my beloved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelf; and at laſt I roſe (in my own time not when he called) to open to my beloved, and he was gone, and then I called him, but he did not anſwer me, I ſought him but did not find him, and oh now my bowels, my bowels is even pained for him, and my ſoul panteth after him even as the hart panteth after the water brooks; Oh that I could but find him whom my ſoul loveth, oh I would hold him, I would hold him faſt, I would not let him go; he ſhould lie all night in my boſom, I would be watchful and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent that I grieve him not, and very fearful of diſpleaſing of him; and would take heed of giving him any cauſe whereby to leave me, and thus to hide his face from me; but oh alaſs for me, when ſhall I find him, when will he come whom I long for? Oh when, when ſhall I have my full enjoyment of him? oh when will he bring me into his banqueting houſe, and his love be even as a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner over me, his left hand under my head, and his right imbraſing of me, ſtaying me with flagons, comforting me with apples, making me ſick of love, giving me of his ſpiſed Wine, and of the juice of his Pomgranets; oh if thus I could come to enjoy him whom my ſoul loveth, then would all tears be wiped away from mine eyes, and I forget my ſorrow becauſe of joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then ſhould I look no more ſorrowful; but ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce as <hi>Hannah</hi> did, and ſay oh my heart rejoyceth in the Lord, and my horn is exalted in the Lord, and my mouth is enlarged over my enemy (who ſaid unto me I ſhould be always barren and unfruitful) becauſe I rejoyce in his ſalvation, who hath regarded my low eſtate; oh now I the barren ſhall bear ſeven, and ſhe who hath had many Children wax feeble, now I the parched ground become a Pool, and I the dry hath ſprings of water, now I the ſoletary place rejoyce, and I the deſart bloſſom as a Roſe; I the poor one made rich, and I the weak one made ſtrong, I the fooliſh one made wiſe, I the empty one overflow with fulneſs; now the days of my ſore mourning turned into joy, and the nights of my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66336:5"/> ſorrow turned into pleaſure, and the ſeaſons of my ſeeking him whom my ſoul loveth turned into times of ſweet repoſes with him in his bed of ſolace: But oh alaſs for me, I may ſpeak of theſe things, but oh when, when will it be thus with me? oh how long ſhall I wait, how long ſhall I ſeek, how long ſhall I call and utter my voice weeping, ſaylng oh come away, come away unto me, thou whom I mourn for, whom I long after, whom my ſoul loveth; oh I have waited ſo long that I am weary, and begin to be almoſt without hope of his coming any more unto me: Well what ſhall I do, and whether ſhall I go, I will even lay me down in ſorrow, and make it my bed, &amp; make grief my ſheets, and tears my pillow, and ſighing and mourning my ſleep untill he come whom my ſoul loveth; for verily I cannot, I cannot be ſatisfied with another beſides him.</p>
               <p>Oh who amongſt the ſons and daughters of Men ſhall I make my moan unto? unto whom ſhall I complain and eaſe my heart unto? where ſhall I find one who is ſenſible of my condition, that can ſimpathize with me, and that can ſpeak a word in ſeaſon unto my poor ſoul, oh is it thus with any as it is with me? Yes, yes, I believe there is many hath been, and many now are in thy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Oh where may I find one of them that I might eaſe my heart unto him, and ſpread my condition before him; for oh veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my bowels is very open to thoſe who be in my condition; well, have patience, be quiet and be ſtill, and lend an ear unto me, and I may ſpeak a little how it is with me, and it may be (if the Lord will) to thy comfort; for oh truly my ſoul loveth thee, oh my heart is moved with compaſſion towards thee, oh my bowels, my bowels is open unto thee, and my ſoul greatly ſimpathize with thy ſoul, and could even wiſh my ſoul (for a time) in thy ſouls ſtead; oh though indeed I am but a Child, yet truly I am in ſome meaſure ſenſible of thy condition, and can read it by my own; and oh how willingly would I help thee according to my ability; oh truly methinks I would even be a help unto all who ſtand in need of help, but eſpecially unto thee thou poor ſoul, what art thou poor, ſo am I; what art thou weak and feeble, ſo am I often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; what art thou empty, ſo am I oftentimes; what art thou cold and barren, ſo am I ſometimes; what art thou as one deſolate and deſtitute, ſo am I ſometimes; what doth thou eat thy bread weeping, and mingle thy drink with thy tears, it is ſo with me at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66336:5"/> ſometimes when I want the enjoyment of him whom my ſoul loveth, for truly it is with me ſometimes as it is with thee; for ſometimes I have not the enjoyment of my beloved as I have at other times, but ſometimes he ſeems to be withdrawn and to hide his face from me, oh then it is with me as it is with thee; oh then ſorrows take hold upon me, and trouble ſurroundeth me about as a wall, and mourning covers me as a garment, and none ſeeth my tears but the Lord; oh then my leanneſs, my leanneſs, my cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and barrenneſs is my greateſt burden, which cauſeth me to go bowed down in ſpirit, ſaying in my heart, Oh whether is my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved gone, and what is the cauſe he hath withdrawn himſelf from me; wherefore is it thus with me, what is the matter, what ſhall I do, what will the Lord leave me, what will my God forſake me, what will the Lord now caſt me off who hath done ſo much for me? Oh what is the cauſe that it is thus with me? wherefore is the windows of Heaven ſhut up, and the ſhoures of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from on high withheld from me? oh once I could ſay the Lord is my ſhepherd, and my ſoul doth not want; he cauſeth me to feed, and even to lie down in green Paſtures, and leadeth me by the ſtill waters, and ſpreadeth my table with dainties, and anointeth my head with the oyle of gladneſs, and cauſeth my cup to overflow with new Wine: But oh alaſs for me now, I am in a dry and thirſty land where no water is; oh what hath the Lord caſt me off for ever; Oh my tears is my meat and drink, whileſt my enemy ſaith unto me where is thy God, doſt thou think he will ever appear again unto thee, why doſt thou thus hunger, thirſt, cry and pant after him; alaſs it is in vain for thee to wait for him; once indeed thou had the enjoyment of him, once thou went with the multitude with them to the houſe of God, with the voice of joy and praiſe with a multitude that keep holy day; but alaſs thou muſt not look for ſuch a day again: And thus the adverſary of my ſoul endeavoureth to add ſorrow to my ſorrow, and to encreaſe the weight of my burden, that ſo I might ſink and never riſe; But oh the Lord my God is near to help me, even in that time when I can ſcarce perceive him, and when I am (as <hi>Peter</hi> was) ready to ſink, then his inviſible arme of mercy is ready to ſave me, and a ſecret hope the Lord preſerveth alive in me, which is as an anchor unto my ſoul, which keeps me from ſuffering ſhipwrack, a hope that the Lord will appear again to me
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66336:6"/> to my joy, whereby ſome encouragement I feel ſtirring in me to wait upon the Lord patiently, and to truſt in him, though I do not ſee him, and to relie upon him and hope in his tender bowels when he ſeems to be far off me, and to roul my ſelf upon him, and ſurely he will appear again to thy joy oh my ſoul, who canſt not be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied without his preſence, even the preſence of the Lord thy God which thou deſireth more then all things elſe whatſoever; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord ſeeing it is ſo with thee that thou deſireth his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence more then all other things; ſurely, ſurely he will not caſt thee off for ever, ſurely he will appear again to thy joy, wherefore why art thou ſo much caſt down oh my ſoul, and why art thou thus diſquieted within me? oh hope, hope thou in thy God, for thou ſhalt yet praiſe him, the Lord will yet again command his loving kindneſs in the day time, and in the night ſeaſon, his ſong ſhall be with thee, even praiſes to the God of thy life; oh wait patiently upon the Lord, and truſt in the living God, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions fails not towards thoſe who loveth him; oh he will ſend out his light and his truth into thee again, and it ſhall bring thee unto his holy hill and to his Tabernacle, and then ſhalt thou go to the altar of God, of God thy exceeding joy, and upon thy harp ſhall thou praiſe the Lord thy God, thy delight and joy, oh it is good for thee both to hope and quietly to wait upon the Lord, for the Lord is good to the man that waits upon him, unto the ſoul which ſeeketh him, and cannot be ſatisfied without him; oh wait patiently upon him even as a ſervant waiteth upon his Maſter, and as a maiden at the hand of her Miſtreſs, ſo do thou wait for the Lord, and even as the Husbandman who ſoweth his ſeed in the Earth hath long patience for it untill he receiveth the early and latter rain; ſo do thou wait patiently upon the Lord who will be unto thee as the early and latter rain in due ſeaſon; wait upon him, he who is to come, will come, and will not tarry, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward will be with him, even fulneſs of joy, comfort, peace, reſt, and ſweet ſatisfaction unto thee oh my ſoul.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul, oh my ſoul, ſurely, ſurely, the Lord will never leave thee nor forſake thee if thou forſake him not; indeed he may ſeem to hide his face from thee for a time, but without doubt he will appear again to thy comfort, who cannot live without him oh my ſoul, the Lord heareth thee often ſaying in ſecret, alaſs what is the glory of the world unto me, what is the honour and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66336:6"/> praiſe of the world to me, what is the favours friendſhip and eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the world to me, what is the vanity, vain ſports, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures of the ſons and daughters of Men to me? oh ſurely all theſe things are but as droſs and dung unto me, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Lord my God who is the fountain of everlaſting joy, delight, and pleaſure; oh if I enjoy him fully I have enough; he is the joying of my heart, the rejoycing and glading of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the ſtrength of my rains, the girdle of my lines; wherefore how can I live without him; oh my ſoul the Lord intends good unto thee by all his dealings with thee, if he withdraw for a time and hide his face from thee for a ſeaſon, it is thereby to let thee ſee what thou art without him, how poor, how weak, how feeble, how fooliſh, how empty, how dead, how dry, how cold, how barren and unfruitful art thou without the Lord, that ſo thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made truly ſenſible of thy own weakneſs and inability may be the more ſenſible of the needfulneſs of the ſupporting power, and upholding arme and ſaving grace of the Lord thy God, and the more to relie and depend upon the Lord; oh my ſoul through the Lords withdrawing his preſence from thee thou comes the more to know what the want of his preſence is, and coms to learn to prize the ſweet enjoyment of his preſence the more, and to hold him faſt and cleave unto him, and to be very vigilent and careful, thou doth not grieve him, nor do the thing that may cauſe him to withdraw himſelf from thee oh my ſoul. Oh my ſoul, thou muſt learn to know how to want, and how to abound, how to be full, and how to be empty, how to be rich, and how to be poor, and in every condition to be content, and not to murmur againſt the Lord; the Lord can open and none can ſhut, and he can ſhut and none can open; the Lord can open the windows of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſhour down abundantly upon thee oh my ſoul, and even make a plenty in thy land, even cauſe thy ſtore to abound with corn, and thy Fats overflow with new wine; and he can alſo ſhut up the windows of heaven for a time, and make a famine in thy Land if he pleaſeth, and thou muſt not ſay unto him (in a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring way) why dealeth thou thus with me? for indeed he may do what he will do, and yet all his doings are juſt and righteous altogether, and in all his dealings with thee, he thy dear, tender nurſing Father, intends good unto thee, oh my ſoul. Oh my ſoul, when the fountain openeth, and the great deep overfloweth, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66336:7"/> fills thee with plenty of things needful for thee, even then oh my ſoul dread and fear thou before the Lord, and take heed of being lifted up in heart, of being puffed up in mind, of being exalted in ſpirit, and beware of a falſe eaſe and wrong liberty and falſe ſecurity, which may ſoon ſteal upon thee at ſuch a time, when thou art rich, wiſe, ſtrong, and full enough in thy own eyes, if thou do not abide upon the watch and dread the Lord, and drink the draughts of joy in the pure fear and trembling, never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting therefrom, in what ever thou enjoy of the Lord, or receive from the Lord, or do and ſuffer for the Lord, keeping low in heart, meek in mind, humble in ſoul, tender in bowels, contrite in ſpirit, and then oh my ſoul thou art in a ſafe condition, truly my ſoul when thou appeareth wiſe, ſtrong, rich and full enough in thy own eye, even then thou art rather in greater danger then when thou appeareth weak, poor and empty in thy own eyes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou art not then without danger, but hath cauſe to fear and watch in all conditions; oh my ſoul when thou appeareth weak, poor and feeble in thy own eyes, even then take heed of diſtruſt and doubting, but hold faſt thy truſt in the Lord, and let thy confidence in his name be firme, and thy hope in his tender bowels be ſure, and conſtantly relie and depend upon him, and honour him in believing in him, and if he kill thee, yet truſt thou in him, and never leave him; for alaſs whether ſhould thou go, he hath the word of eternal life, who is worthy to be glorified, magnified, honoured and praiſed, feared, ſerved, loved and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever, and forever more: Oh my ſoul thou dearly loveth thy Fathers Children; oh the Lord knoweth how near and dear his dear babes and tender lambs are unto thee oh my ſoul; oh thou knoweth them in the ſpirit of love, wherein thou delighteth to imbrace them (even thoſe whom (outwardly) thou never ſaw) and (in ſpirit) to claſp them about, and kiſs them with a kiſs of peace, and hug them in the boſom of indearedneſs; ah thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, thy bowels is open unto them, and thy love is dear indeed towards them as the Lord thy God knoweth; and oh that love might abound in thee more and more, and in the hearts of all the children of Light, it may abound one towards another, as in days paſt, and years which are gone, that it may appear to all, we are of God who is love, and that we all are true diſciples of Chriſt, in that we love one another, not only in ſhew and in word, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66336:7"/> in deed and in truth, loving one another fervently with a pure heart.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul, thou deſireſt to ſimpathize with thy Fathers Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; in their tryals, ſufferings and afflictions; and (in ſpirit) to bear a part with them therein; oh thou deſireſt, even to mourne with them that mourne, and to weep with them that weep in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and to rejoyce with them that rejoyce, and to travel in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with and for the Travellers to Sion, and with the Travellers in Sion, and to watch with thoſe Watch-men, which the Lord hath ſet (upon the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who for Sions ſake cannot be ſtill, and for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſake, cannot hold their peace; who ceaſe not to cry day and night to the Lord, and can give him no reſt, until he eſtabliſh Jeruſalem, and make her a praiſe in the whole Earth for ever more.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul, be watchful and wary, that thou doſt not in the leaſt degree, ſeek glory, honor, and praiſe to thy ſelf; and to be had in eſteem by others; but oh wait to feel ſelf, wholly bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into death, and made of no reputation; and take heed that thy left hand, know not, what thy right hand doth; and do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſeen of men, or whereby to be accounted of by others; but in all thou doth, appeal unto him, who ſeeth in ſecret; and he it is, who will reward thee openly; ſeek thou to be only known, and manifeſted, to the pure un-erring witneſs of God, in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; and to ſtand juſtified and approved by it, and that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; no honor, no glory, no praiſe, but to God alone, oh ſtrive not, for Lordſhip, and Maſterſhip over others; but rather ſtrive to be moſt meekeſt, loweſt, humbleſt, tender and contrite in mind, and ſpirit, condeſcending even to the loweſt, and ſerving the meaneſt, in love; ſeeking peace, and unity among bretheren, with all ſelf-denyal; bearing, forbearing, and forgiving for the Seeds ſake; bearing with the infirmities of the weak, and with the haltings of the feeble, watching for the good, in all, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons; but not to watch for evil, in any, for that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, in the eyes of the Lord; and ſeek thou the glory of God alone, the honor of his name; the exaltation and ſpreading forth of his truth; the freedome, growth, and reign of the Seed of God, in the hearts of all; the proſperity of his tender Lambs, Babes and Children, that they may all ſtand, in this day of tryal;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66336:8"/> and be preſerved in this hour of darkneſs, and temptation; and even to ſeek the good of all; yea the good of thy greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and have nothing but love and good will towards thy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Perſecuters; ſeeking the ſalvation of all people, but not the deſtruction of any.</p>
               <p>And oh my ſoul, be circumſpect, and vigilent, to walk ſo as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the Goſpel, and thee to be an adorning to the truth of God; and to be as an holy example, and righteous pattern unto all people, where ever I come, that I may be unto the Lord, as a ſweet ſmell, and delectable ſavour, that the bleſſing of the Lord my God, may be poured down upon me, yet more and more, that I might become fruitful unto the Lord my God, and be an inſtrument in his hand amongſt the Sons and Daughters of Men, to the praiſe, glory, honor, and renown of the Lord Almighty, for ever more; oh my ſoul, watch and fear, before the Lord, and take heed thou do not that thing to pleaſe others, which thou knoweſt is not approved by the Lord; keep thy eye unto the Lord, and look not out at others, to walk by imitation, and if thou ſeeth him or her, one or another, what ever they be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of; do thoſe things, which the Lord allowes thee not to do; do not thee do them, becauſe an other doth them; but watch and keep cloſe unto the Lord, and take counſel of him.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul, do not judg, or juſtifie thoſe things, which thou hath not a true diſcerning in; becauſe an other judges or juſtifies them, but rather be paſſive in that matter, and ſtand ſtill and wait upon the Lord for a perfect underſtanding in all things.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul, ſeek not liberty to the fleſh, beware of that, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted freedome, which is indeed bondage, which hath ſtollen upon many in their latter days; oh my ſoul, indeavour to put off thoſe things, which in their place, are ſaid to be lawful, which are a means to hinder thy growth into the Eternal: and oh, walk wiſely before all Men, giving no offence to the Jew nor Gentile, nor to the Church in God, knowing that there is that, which is lawful, but not expedient; there is that which is lawful, but it edifies not; wherefore forbear what may be forborn; and yet be not brought under the power of any thing below the life, but ſeek after thoſe things, which make for edification, love, peace and unity; for God is the Author of peace, and not the Author of confuſion, ſtrife, contention and debate; Oh my ſoul, thou doth greatly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66336:8"/> deſire, that I might not appear, in the ſight of any of the Lords Lambs, and little ones; to be more, then what I really am in and through the grace of God, by which I am what I am, and his grace which he hath freely beſtowed upon me hath not been in vain, praiſes to his name for ever; Oh I would not be accounted of by any little one to be more then what I am in the Lord, but rather let me be hid, leaſt honour ſhould be aſcribed unto that, unto which it doth not belong; for indeed all honour belongs to God alone; alaſs all fleſh is as graſs, and what is Man, he is but a Veſſel wherein God may appear or diſappear as he pleaſeth, and indeed the Lord is jealous of his glory, and he will not give it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another; wherefore my ſoul ſeek the glory, honour and praiſe to God alone, unto whom only it is due for ever and ever more. Oh my ſoul, thou doth not want the love, the dear unfained love of the Lords dear babes, tender lambs and children, and oh thou deſireth thou may not want their prayers for thee oh my ſoul, that I may be preſerved in this day of trial, and be enabled by the Lord to finiſh my Teſtimony for him to his praiſe and my comfort, joy and peace for ever more.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul fear thou before the living God, and very diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take heed leaſt thou who ſtand'ſt ſhould fall as ſeveral hath done, to their own woe, and to the diſhonour of God, and to the cauſing his unchangable Truth to be evil ſpoken of, and many ſeekers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Righteouſneſs to ſtumble, and the hands of Sions enemies thereby ſtrengthened againſt the faithful of the Lord, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe hearts are made ſad, whom the Lord hath not made ſad; even in the ſenſe of the ſad condition of thoſe, who once in ſome meaſure were acquainted with the Lord, once taſted of his goodneſs, and graciouſneſs, of his ſweet unſpeakable love and peace, and even in ſome meaſure, taſted and handled of the word of life; and of the Powers of the World to come; who were delivered out of ſpiritual Egypt, by an out-ſtretched Arm, and Mighty Power, and by the ſame power carried through the Spiritual ſea and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and did in meaſure eat of the ſpiritual meat and drink of the Spiritual Rock which was made unto them as a pillar of fire by night, and a pillar of a cloud by day, &amp;c. and yet behold they are drawn back again by the enemy of their ſoul, through their yielding unto his temptations, and receiving his proffers, and are turned as the Dog to his vomit, and as the ſow that was waſhed
<pb facs="tcp:66336:9"/> to her wallowing again in the mire; and hath even made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of faith and a good conſcience, and are proved treacherous children, denying their father who begat them, and caſting off their mother who traveled in pain to bring them forth, and hating the womb that bore them, and paps which gave them ſuck, &amp; this hath come upon them through careleſneſs and ſloathfulneſs, and through reaſoning and conſulting with the enemy of their ſouls, and through looking at the trouble, trial, ſufferings, ſtreights, and difficulties which appeared in their way, and through luſting after the fleſh pots of <hi>Egipt</hi> through looking back into the eaſe, pleaſure, riches and honour of this world, which hath carried them away captive again into <hi>Egipt</hi> into the houſe of bondage again; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oh my ſoul watch, watch and ſtand faſt in that liberty which the truth Chriſt the power of God hath brought thee into, and take heed thou be not again intangled with the yoak of bondage.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul if there be ſome who once were freſh, green, tender living and fruitful unto God, who now hath loſt their freſhneſs, greenneſs, tenderneſs and fruitfulneſs towards God, and now coldneſs, deadneſs, and barrenneſs is come upon them to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and their love and zeal for the Lord waxed cold; Oh my ſoul if it have thus happened unto ſome, oh how can thou but fear before the Lord, oh my ſoul leaſt the ſame ſhould happen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee alſo.</p>
               <p>And if ſome there be whoſe minds are gotten into a full liberty, and are at eaſe in the fleſh, living above the croſs of Chriſt Jeſus, which crucifies to the world, and are grown careleſs and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, ſpending their time often with vain talking, fooliſh jeſting, and needleſs communication, who formerly ſpent their time in waiting upon the Lord in meditating and exerciſing themſelves in the things of God, being very watchful over their thoughts, words, works and actions, having the pure fear of the Righteous God freſh in their hearts, ſtanding in awe of him always, leaſt they ſhould ſin againſt him in thought, word and deed, lying down and riſing up in his pure fear, eating and drinking, and doing all things in the pure fear of the Lord, knowing a ſtay to their minds, a ſtop to their thoughts, a bridle to their tongues, a watch before their mouth, and a fearing in their hearts, leaſt they ſhould not be watchful enough over their lives and converſations, yea even over their very carriage and geſture, their words being very few,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66336:9"/> ſober and ſavoury, even ſavouring of the grace of God in their hearts, they deſiring and endeavouring very diligently to walk ſo as that they might in life, carriage and converſation be as holy patterns and righteous examples of love, of peace, of holineſs and purity, of meekneſs and lowlineſs, of tenderneſs and pitty, of mercy and compaſſion, of patience and long ſuffering, of ſobriety and gentleneſs, &amp;c. that ſo they might walk as becometh Saints, blameleſs and harmleſs, as ſons of God without rebuke, in the middeſt of a crooked and perverſe generation, among whom to ſhine as lights to the adorning of the truth of God profeſſed by them, and to the glory, honour and praiſe of the Lord God, and to the joy, comfort, refreſhment, peace and conſolation of their own ſouls: Oh this condition which once they were in was very ſweet, bleſſed and happy; and if now they have in meaſure loſt this ſweet condition, and ſo in meaſure are departed from their firſt love, and grown careleſs and negligent, puft up with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge without life, which only keeps humble, ſatisfying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with talking of what they formerly enjoyed of the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd of what they have done and ſuffered for the Lord, &amp;c. I ſay if it be thus with ſome, then oh my ſoul in the ſence of what is come upon them, how can thou but fear, dread and tremble in heart before the Lord, not in the leaſt meaſure or degree to watch for evil in any, or to have an eye open to ſpy out the nakedneſs of another, or to take an occaſion againſt them becauſe of their fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and haltings, or being b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſie in looking at others conditions; and in keeping their Vinyards and neglect the keeping of thy own: Nay, nay, oh my Soul, let it not be ſo with thee; but if thou (as thou ſetteth in thy habitation without deſiring at all to look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad at others) ſeeth that it hath and is happened unto many according as is forementioned; then oh my ſoul only let it be as a warning unto thee the more to fear before the Lord, and to be the more watchful in the light, and to keep cloſer unto the Lord, leaſt the ſame things ſhould happen unto thee oh my ſoul as hath happened unto them; unto whom let thy tenderneſs extend, and thy dear love abound with ſecret crys, and ſtrong groanings unto the Lord thy God on their behalfes, and on thy own behalf, that thou may be kept and preſerved unto the end: Oh alaſs for thee my poor ſoul, how weak art thou, and how unable to ſtand as of thy ſelf; wherefore cleave, cleave, and keep cloſe unto the Lord,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66336:10"/> thy tender compaſſionate God, and then aſſuredly the Lord will cleave unto thee, and will not leave thee oh my ſoul; wherefore lift up thy head in the ſtrength of the Lord, and look up unto the holy one, whoſe dwelling is on high in the holy place; and with thee oh my ſoul, as thou art kept humble in heart, contrite in ſpirit, meek in mind, and trembleth at his word: and look not at thy own weakneſs, feebleneſs and inability, but keep thy eye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and truſt in his name, relie and depend upon his arme, and hope in his tender bowels; who maketh the poor rich, the weak ſtrong, the ſimple wiſe; wait thou patiently upon him, and look not out at the greatneſs of others meaſures; neither look thou at the ſmallneſs of thy own, leaſt faintneſs, wearineſs, and diſcouragement ſhould thereby come in upon thee, and thou mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur becauſe thy meaſure is no greater, but be thou contented, and truly ſatisfied with thy portion, and be faithful unto the Lord in thy meaſure, and being faithful in the little, thou ſhall be made ruler over much, and enter into the joy of the Lord, wait upon him, who hath freely given in thee what thou hath of him, and he can give thee more; there was nothing in thee (that was of thee) which induced the Lord to communicate that meaſure of his fulneſs unto thee which he hath diſpenſed to thee, but of his own meer mercy, tender love and free grace, who of his own free will hath begotten thee again unto a living hope, ſo that thou right well knoweth that it is not he that willeth nor he that runeth, but God who ſheweth mercy; Oh thou had not awakened out of the ſleep of ſin and corruption, had not the mighty God thundred from his dwelling place upon thee and awakened thee oh my ſoul, ſurely thou had never been raiſed out of the duſt of ſin, and grave of iniquity had not the Lord of his own free will raiſed thee up, and brought thee forth by his own Almighty power; Oh my ſoul ſurely thou had never as (as of thy ſelf) turned unto the Lord, had not the Lord of his own free will turned thee, and after thou was turned thou repented, and after thou was afflicted thou ſmote upon thy thigh, yea thou was confounded becauſe thou bore the ſhame of thy youth; and ſurely my ſoul after the Lord had turned thee in meaſure unto him, thou had not followed him in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſtrait way, through the Croſs in the ſelf denial, had not the Lord thy God drawn thee after him by the cords and woings of his tender love; and ſurely thou had turned back again from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66336:10"/> the Lord into the mire and durt again, and had never ſtood untill this hour, but muſt have fainted and dyed ere this day, had not the Lord of his own free will kept thee, preſerved thee, upheld thee, and ſupported thee by his own almighty power, whoſe grace hath been ſufficient for thee, both in the day of proſperity, and in the day of adverſity, in the time of tryal, in the hour of temptation; and ſo let all fleſh be ſilent in thee oh my ſoul, and the Lord only exalted, and the boaſter for ever excluded, and God alone have the glory, and ſelf wholly ſlain, and the Lord alone honoured and praiſed, and his unſpeakable love and free grace admired, and his holy name feared and obeyed, by whoſe grace thou art what thou art, and his grace beſtowed upon thee hath not been in vain; bleſſed, bleſſed be the Lord, and pure, holy praiſes to him, and glory, and Halleluiah to him in the higheſt, Amen ſaith my ſoul. Oh Lord what was I, and what was my Fathers houſe, I was neither a Prophet nor a Prophets ſon; what was I, that the King of glory ſhould caſt his eye upon me, even when I laid as among the pits; what was I that he ſhould hold forth the ſcepter unto me, and I ſhould find favour in his ſight, who regarded my low eſtate, and raiſed me out of the duſt, and brought me from off the dunghill to ſit among Princes.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul the Lord hath done much for thee ſince the day he formed thee in the womb, and brought thee forth for his praiſe; he hath made the crooked things ſtrait before thee, and rough ſmooth, and mountains he hath laid low before thee, and removed many a hill out of thy way, and he hath made a way for thee in the Wilderneſs, and a path through many a thicket, he hath lopt the bough with terrour, and the great one of ſtature hath been hewn down, he did cut up the thicket of the Forreſt with Iron, and Lebanon did fall by a mighty one; oh he hath made the hard things eaſie unto thee; oh how hath his love made thee willing to bow thy neck to the yoak, and to take up the Croſs, and totally to deſpiſe the ſhame, and to follow the Lamb through ſome trials and tribulations, whoſe love hath drawn thee after him, whoſe love hath (as it were) made thee to forget thy Fathers houſe; Oh how hath his love cauſed me to caſt off other lovers, and to love the Lord my God, who is now become my treaſure, and my heart is with him; ſo that if I be ſhut up in priſon, if I enjoy him; oh then days, months and years may paſs over my head, and time
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66336:11"/> is not thought long nor ſufferings hard, becauſe of the enjoyment of the preſence of the Lord my treaſure, whom my ſoul loveth, for whoſe ſake I am willing to ſuffer; whoſe pure ſweet refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comfortable preſence makes a priſon delightſome to me; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, pure living praiſes to my God for ever, who hath been with me in ſix troubles, and in the ſeventh he hath not left me; he is my buckler, my ſhield, my ſtrength, my Rock, my ſafe guard, my ſtrong t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer; wherefore I'le not fear the threats of the wicked, neither regard the cruelty of the ungodly, nor heed the purpoſes of my enemy; nor mind the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terminations of unrighteous men, through the ſtrength of my God I will not fear, though the Earth be removed and carried into the midſt of the Sea; and though the mountains ſhake through the ſwelling thereof; though the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then rage, and the people imagine vain things, and the Rulers take councel againſt me, I'le not fear what Man can do unto me, for the Lord is with me, and I ſhall not be moved; and the Lord will help me, and that right early; yet alaſs for me poor, poor worm, I am but a child weak and feeble, but indeed having had great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the love of my God, and of his tender fatherly care over me, how can I but confidently truſt, hope, relie and depend upon the Lord my God, believing that he the mighty one will enable me the weak one to wade through and endure thoſe tryals he pleaſeth to exerciſe me withal; who through his love and mercy hath cauſed my trials to work for my good praiſes to his name for ever more; who hath nine times delivered me out of the hands of unreaſonable men, out of their priſons and holes, where I have ſuffered for the Teſtimony of my God, through his enabling of me without murmuring againſt him; praiſes unto him alone; no honour, no honour, no glory, but unto God ſaith my ſoul, who hath kept me by his power from bowing to the Beaſt, or drinking of the Whores Cup; pure praiſes to my dear God for ever more, who will free me once again from bonds in his own time. I am willing to wait thy ſeaſon oh my God, who art with me; and oh let me never depart from thee oh Lord, and then I know thou will never leave me, but thou wilt be my God to help me ſtill, and to ſupport me ſtill, and to comfort me ſtill, and refreſh me ſtill, and quicken me ſtill, and to feed me ſtill with bread from Heaven, freſh Manna morning by morning, and give me to drink of the River of thy pleaſure daily; who wilt enable me to ſtand
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66336:11"/> faithful to thee unto the end of my days, that I may finiſh my Teſtimony for thee, thy name and truth in this thy day, even with joy, and lay down my head in peace, in thy tender boſome of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs love oh my tender God, and therein repoſe with thy dear Children for evermore; &amp; have my full ſatisfaction of love in thee, thou fountain of Love, and therein fetch my full breath for ever more; Oh let it be ſo, oh let it be ſo, oh my dear God for thy own ſeed ſake, to thy own praiſe thou holy one, who is worthy, worthy of all glory, glory, honour and everlaſting thankſgiving, and pure living praiſes for ever, and ever more, Amen, Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiah, glory and eternal renown to the almighty one in the higheſt, Amen.</p>
               <p>Oh my ſoul thou dearly loveth the whole Flock of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are ſcattered upon the face of the Earth; oh thou great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſireth their proſperity and tranquility, and that the Lord may proſper and bleſs them with all Spiritual bleſſings in Chriſt Jeſus: Oh the Lord God keep all his Children every where in this hour and power of darkneſs, and preſerve all his dear babes and tender lambs in this day of great trial and manifold temptation; Oh the Lord keep all thoſe who make mention of his name in ſincerity and truth, from bowing in the leaſt degree unto the Beaſt, and from drinking the leaſt drop of the Whores cup, although ſhe ſhould be permitted to drink their blood; Oh the Lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty keep his ſheep and lambs who were once ſcattered abroad, in the cloudy dark day, whom he hath ſought and found out, and gathered out of the deſart places, and waſt howling Wilderneſs, whom he hath brought from off the barren mountains and dry heaths into the low, low, low freſh green Valley, where the pure ſweet refreſhing conſolating ſprings of life eternal encompaſſeth them about; Oh the Lord keep them ſtill and quiet, minding their feeding, and not at all heed the raging of the Sea, nor regard the unmercyful waves thereof, which often looks very high, as if they would quite overflow the valley of the low places, and drown all who flee not unto the mountains for refuge and ſafety; but oh let not the ſheep and lambs, and little ones fear, nor at all flee to the hills for refuge, for behold the Lord the high and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one, the holy one of Iſrael is their Shepherd, and he even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually watcheth over them, and greatly careth for them, and he it is who hath given bounds to the raging Sea, and he limits
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66336:12"/> the proud waves thereof, and ſhuteth up her floods as he pleaſeth; he can let forth the wind, and ſuffer a ſtorm, and he can make a calm when he pleaſeth, he can cauſe the ſea and the wind to obey him; and therefore the Children of God need not to fear none beſides the Lord, who will ſuffer nothing to befall them but what ſhall work for good to all his choſen faithful ones; wherefore it is good for all the Children of the Lord confidently to truſt in the Lord and not at all fear, though their enemies purſue hard after them, and ſay in their hearts, come, come, we will purſue them, we will overtake them, our luſts ſhall be ſatisfied upon them, we will have the deſire of our hearts concerning them, we will draw our ſwords, and our hands ſhall deſtroy them, and we will try whether their Gods (in whom they ſay they truſt) be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the ſtroke of our hands; well let not Iſrael heed the boaſting and threatnings of his enemies; nor regard the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of his adverſaries, though they purſue hard after him, and ſay we will bring them back again into Egypt, or elſe we will total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy them; yet let not Iſrael fear, for the Lord his God is between him, and his enemies, and fights for him againſt his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and he in his anger will look down upon them, and trouble their hoſt, and take off their Chariot wheels, and will blow in his wrath upon them, and the ſea of his righteous indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall cover them, and they ſhall ſink as lead in the bottom of his righteous Judgments, and he will get himſelf a name through the diſtruction of Sions enemies, and honour and magnifie himſelf through the deliverance of his choſen, who will work wonders for the ſake of his Redeemed, in ſo much as the Dukes of Edom ſhall be amazed, and even trembling ſhall take hold upon the mighty men of Moab, and all Nations ſhall ſhiver and quake before the mighty God of Iſrael, who is dreadful in holineſs, fearful in praiſes, doing wonders: Oh let Iſrael honour his God in believing in him, and in truſting in his name, in relying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon his arme of everlaſting ſtrength, and patiently without murmurings to wait upon the Lord, for he that is to come will come, and will not tarry, whoſe work is before him, and his reward is with him, even joy for the mourners in Sion, and beauty for aſhes, gladneſs for the heavy hearted in Jeruſalem, freedom for bondage, freedom from weights, burdens and grievous oppreſſions.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:66336:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> Oh let all the Children of the Lord wait without fainting upon the Lord, for yet a little while and the voice will be heard, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rejoyce, oh rejoyce, and even ſing for joy ye ſaints, ſervants, and prophets of the moſt high, and triumph in the Lord Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over the beaſt and falſe prophet, and over the Whore which hath corrupted the Earth, who hath long ſet as a queen, and ſaid in her heart, ſhe ſhould never ſee ſorrow, with whom the Nations of the Earth hath committed fornication, and ſhe hath made Nations, Kindreds, Tongues and People drunk with the wine of her fornication, who hath long deceived the Nations with her golden cup which hath been filled with abominations, and in her is found all the blood of the Martyrs, and ſervants of Jeſus, which hath been ſhed upon the earth, and ſhe hath rid upon the beaſt that roſe out of the Sea, who received his ſeat, great power and authority from the Dragon, who perſecuted the true woman that was cloathed with the ſun, and had a crown of twelve Stars upon her head, who ſought to devour her Man child, and made war againſt the remnant of her ſeed, who keep the commands of God, and have the Teſtimony of Jeſus, theſe cannot worſhip the beaſt nor his name, nor receive his mark, but theſe worſhip God alone, and are followers of the Lamb through many tribulations, whoſe garments are made white in his blood, by whom they are redeemed from amongſt men, theſe the Beaſt and falſe Prophet have ſought, to kill, perſecute and root out from off the face of the earth; but wo, wo, wo, to the beaſt, falſe prophet, and thè Whore, for the day of their Judgment is come, and miſery, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, diſtreſs and deſtruction is coming upon them, and ſhe the mother of Harlots, the mother of Witchcrafts, the abominations of the earth ſhall utterly be deſtroyed, and totally burnt with fire, for ſtrong is the Lord God Almighty who judgeth her, and now ſing oh Heavens and rejoyce ye who live therein, over myſtery Babylon the great, for it is fallen, it is fallen as a mighty milſtone into the bottom of the Sea, never more to ariſe again, Amen, Halleluiah.</p>
               <p>The Lord will thunder from Heaven upon thy enemies oh Sion, and will break thy adverſaries to pieces, and will give ſtrength to thy King, and exalt the horne of his Anointed, and he ſhall reign and rule, and proſper, and execute juſtice and true judgment in the earth, in his days Judah ſhall be ſaved, and Iſrael ſhall dwell
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66336:13"/> ſafely, and ſit under his own Vine, and none ſhall make him afraid; then ſhall it be ſaid to Jeruſalem fear not, and to Sion, let not thy hands be ſlack, the Lord in the middeſt of thee is mighty, he hath ſaved thee, he hath ſet thee free from thy trouble, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over thee with joy, he'l joy over thee with ſinging, then it ſhall be ſaid, ſing oh daughter of Sion, and ſhout oh Iſrael, and rejoyce with all thy heart oh daughter of Jeruſalem, for the Lord hath taken away thy Judgment, he hath caſt out thy enemies, and thy warfare is accompliſhed, and thy great travel is finiſhed, and now thou ſhalt reſt from thy labour, and they who hath laboured and mourned with thee and for thee ſhall rejoyce for joy with thee, and ſuck and be ſatisfied with the ſweet conſolation of thy breaſt, and milk out and be delighted in the abundance of thy glory; oh the Lord thy husband, thy maker, the God of hoſts is his name, will extend peace, joy, comfort, and everlaſting refreſhment as a mighty ſtream, and endleſs conſolation as a river; oh then ſhall they be comforted in thee after their ſorrow, and be born up upon thy ſides, and dandles upon thy knees; for as a woman comforteth her only ſon, ſo will the Lord comfort Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; in the ſence whereof her Children ſhall rejoyce, and their ſouls be right glad, and flouriſh as an herb, and their ſpirit ſhall praiſe and ſing glory unto him who is Lord and King of Heaven and Earth, who is worthy, worthy of all glory, praiſe and honour for ever, and for ever more, Amen ſaith my ſoul.</p>
               <p>The thing which the Lord hath purpoſed muſt be accompliſhed in his ſeaſon, and the thing that he hath determined muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in deſpite of all the powers of Darkneſs; Oh that all thy babes and lambs may willingly wait thy appointed time oh Lord God almighty, oh dear God keep all thy people retire in thy name, that ſo what ever thou ſuffer to befall their bodies, their ſouls may be ſafe bundeled up in the bundle of Life, wrapped therein for ever more, for a terrible day is like to be upon all fleſh, and who can be able to abide it? Oh dear God increaſe the patience of thy People, ſtrengthen the faith of thy Choſen; oh ſupport the weak, and uphold the little ones, which cannot yet go alone; oh that none of thy flock may faint, nor grow weary; oh that all thine might ſtand in the day of tryal, and be kept in the hour of temptation, and borne up under all ſufferings, that ſo in the end they may come forth as gold ſeven
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66336:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> times refined in the fire, that they may ſhine as ſtars in the firmament of thy power, making mention of thy goodneſs, graciouſneſs and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs oh Lord God Almighty, declaring of thy mighty acts, and ſing of thy mercies and wonderful doings, and glorifie, magnifie, honour and praiſe thee, thou mighty everlaſting powerful one, who art from all Eternity to all Eternity, whoſe Throne is eſtabliſhed of old, whoſe ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beareth ſway in Righteouſneſs, whoſe Kingdom is Everlaſting glory and halleluiah to thee in the higheſt, for ever and for ever mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, yea praiſes, praiſes, pure living praiſes every minute, be rendered unto the Lord Almighty, ſaith the ſoul of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Bennit.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>OH ariſe, ariſe, thou holy righteous ſeed of the Covenant of life eternal; Ariſe, ariſe, thy Light is come, and the glory of thy God is riſen upon thee; Oh thou lovely one, Nations ſhall come to thy light, and Kings to the brightneſs of thy riſing; Ah thou beautiful one, thy Sons ſhall come from far, and thy Daughters from the ends of the Earth; Ariſe, ariſe thou beautiful one, who art altogether lovely: Oh how ſweet is thy Love thou lovely one, oh how excellent is thy Love thou choice one; oh thy love, thy love is more precious then Rubies, more ſweeter then hony, oh thy love is better then wine; Oh how hath thy love overcome the hearts of many, and wone them unto thee, oh thy love draws many after thee; oh how doth thy love cauſe many to caſt off all their other lovers to follow thee thou lovely one; oh thou art become unto many ſouls (who loveth thee thou lovely one) even the chiefeſt of ten thouſands, whoſe eyes are opened to ſee thy beauty, and to behold thy comelineſs thou beautiful one; oh thou art hid from the polluted, neither can the unclean behold thy excellent beauty, the Vulterous eye cannot perceive thy Comelineſs, nor they who hath eyes full of Adultery, and cannot ceaſe from ſin, and have hearts exerciſed with covetous practiſes, and are gone a whoring after many Lovers; oh from theſe thou art hid thou lovely one, even as a garden incloſed, as a ſpring ſhut up as a fountain ſealed from them: Oh ariſe thou choice one, and let thy beauty appear unto thoſe who yet hath not ſeen thy beauty; and let them taſt of thy love, that ſo they may caſt off all other Lovers, and follow thee; Caſt of all, and cleave unto thee with their whole hearts. Oh ariſe, ariſe thou beloved one, and ſhine forth in thy excellent glory, that even the Nations may be raviſhed with thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Kingdoms overcome with thy love, and be drawn after thee,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66336:14"/> that a bleſſing in thee they may obtain; Oh ariſe and let thy fruitfulneſs appear thou p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecious one, and let joy and gladneſs fill thy heart thou lovely one, for the days of thy rejoycing is come and coming, and the days of thy mourning is fleeing away; Oh thou beloved one thou hath been even as a woman fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaken, and grieved in ſpirit, and few or none of the ſons and daughters of Men hath looked upon thee with an eye of pitty; Oh thou hath been as the Owle in the deſart, and as the alone ſparrow upon the houſe top, and as the alone quail in the ſtuble fields, and as a Dove mourning alone without her Mat; who hath ſet ſolitary alone as in the Wilderneſs, and none among the ſons of Men to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t thee, oh thou beloved one; thou hath been like unto a man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and very deeply acquainted with grief, often ſmitten, often grieved often afflicted, often wounded, often pierced and oppreſſed, even as a Cart that is preſſed with ſheaves, and yet the ſons and daughters of Men hath eſteemed thee not, although indeed thou patient one thou hath been wounded by their tranſgreſſions, and grieved, ſmitten and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ced, and bruiſed by their iniquities, and hath born the weight of their ſins, and the burden of their Tranſgreſſions, even while they like ſheep have gone aſtray, every one following his own way, and feaſting themſelves as for a day of ſlaughter, whiles thou hath been mourning becauſe of the iniquity of the people; eating and drinking and riſing up to play, whiles thou hath been weeping and groaning in ſecret, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the multitude of their tranſgreſſions, who hath heaped ſin upon ſin, and iniquity upon iniquity, and hath loaded thee therewith, which hath been as an impreſs of ten thouſands upon thee thou tender one, and unto thee they had no regard, they took no notice of thy ſorrow and burdens: But oh thou beloved one, thy God, thy tender God, who loveth thee with an Everlaſting love, took notice of thy ſorrow, and he ſaw thy grief, and beheld thy ſore weights and burdens, and took cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of thy grievous oppreſſions, and he heard the voice of thy weeping, and thy tears which thou dropped upon his altar, laid in the view of the eye of his pittiful ſoul, and he beheld thy great travel, and thy ſighing and groaning ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed into his ears, and his tender, tender bowels of infinite love, mercy, pitty and everlaſting compaſſion was and is moved towards thee, and he hath determined to comfort thee with an everlaſting comfort, thou patient ſuffering one, and the nights of thy ſorrow ſhall vaniſh away for ever, and the days of thy mourning ſhall be over. Oh thou beloved one, lift up thy head, lift up thy head, in the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength of thy God, and gird up thy loynes with courage in the power of his might, for thy winter is almoſt over and gone, and ſhall no
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66336:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> more come, the ſtorms are vaniſhing away, and ſhall no more appear, the nipping froſts are diſſolving by the Son of Righteouſneſs, who is ariſen upon thee with healing in his wings; Ah lift up thy voice like the ſound of a Trumpet, and ſhout like the voice of a King, and ſing for joy thou beloved one, for thy ſpring is come thou lovely one, thy ſummer is come thou lovely one, the ſinging of birds is come thou beautiful one, and the voice of the Turtle is heard in thy land thou delicate and choice one; let thy heart be filled with melody thou bleſſed one, who art cloathed with chaſtity, and keepeth thy Virginity in the Chamber of Purity; oh thy beloved is come and into his banqueting houſe he is bringing thee, where his banner over thee is love, where he will ſtay thee with flagons, &amp; comfort thee with apples, and cauſe thee to drink of his ſpiced wine, and of the juice of his Pomgranets; Oh rejoyce thou in his love thou lovely one, for the days of the glading of thy heart is come, thou tender one who hath been toſſed with tempeſt and not comforted, thou hath been termed deſolate and forſaken, thou hath been as one barren and unfruitful; But now ariſe, ariſe, lengthen thy cords, and ſtrengthen thy ſtakes, and enlarge the curtains of thy habitation; for lo thou fruitful one thou ſhalt break forth on the right hand &amp; on the left, and thy ſeed ſhall inherit the Gentiles, and thy off-ſpring the people; the North ſhall give up, and the South ſhall not keep back; they ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and flock unto thee as Doves to the window; thy ſons ſhall come from far, and thy daughters be nurſed at thy ſides, thou ſhalt cauſe many waſt places to be builded, and many buildings to fall, and deſolate places to be inhabited, and inhabited pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be laid deſolate, and barren mountains to become fruitful vallys, and fruitful places to become barren mountains, and the wilderneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Vinyard of ſweet Grapes, the forreſt as a Citty of habitation, the parched ground to become a pool, and dry heaths ſprings of water; oh ariſe, ariſe, thou beloved one, and let thy fruitfulneſs be manifeſted to the Nations, break forth in thy excellent glory, ſhine forth in thy glorious beauty as clear as the morning without clouds, fair as the Moon, and bright as the Sun, that thou may appear as a royal Diadem in the hand of the Lord, and as a Crown of glory in the hand of thy God, that far off Nations may ſee thy beauty, and remote Kings may ſee thy excellent glory, and be wone by thy love unto thee, that they who hath hated thee may love thee, becauſe of thy love which did extend to them, even whilſt they hated thee and rejected the woings of thy love; oh my ſoul loves thee in thy love thou lovely one; oh kiſs me, kiſs me, with the kiſſes of thy mouth, for thy love is better then wine; oh thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66336:15"/> beautiful one thy love overcomes my heart, thy love draweth me after thee; oh thou art pleaſant unto me, thy preſence is more deſirable then all things my heart can deſire; oh if thou hide thy face thou bountiful one then am I bowed down, for the ſmiles of thy comely countenance is the rejoycing of my heart, and the glading of my ſoul, the refreſhing of my ſpirit as marrow to my bones, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength to my reins; oh thou art my joy in ſorrow, my comfort in mourning, my help in need, my ſtrength in weakneſs, my riches in poverty, my bread in hunger, my water in thirſt, my refuge from ſtorms, my ſhelter from heat, and as the ſhadow of a Rock to me in a weary land; oh how can I but love thee in thy love thou lovely one, oh thou art my mother who hath traveled in great pain to bring me forth, thou art the womb that bore me, and the paps that giveth me ſuck, the cradle of my reſt, and the bed of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; oh can I forget thee, how can I forget thee who hath done ſo much for me, even that which no man could do; oh thou loved me firſt before I loved thee thou lovely one, and with thy love thou woed me; and by thy love thou overcame my heart and drew it after thee, and now thou amiable one, the deſire of my ſoul is unto thee, and unto the remembrance of thy love; oh my ſoul deſireth thee in the night ſeaſon, and in the morning I will ſeek thee early; thou art as a cluſter of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, and as a bundle of Mirre unto me, thou ſhall lie all night between my breaſts; oh thou lovely one let me repoſe in thy boſom, and fould me in thy armes; oh thy love, thy love overcomes my heart, thy beauty even makes me ſick of love; oh let me remember thy love more then Wine, it is the upright loves thee, and it is the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in heart who ſeeth thy beauty, &amp; beholdeth thy excellent comel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs, oh let thy love ſtill draw me after thee, oh let me never leave thee; oh that I may never forſake thee, nor be unmindful of thy love which I have known to be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onger then death, and him who hath the power of death; Oh thou art a tree of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe to thoſe who taketh hold on thee, and bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d is every ſoul that retaineth thee: Oh thy ways are ways of pleaſantneſs, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d all thy paths are green and delightſome to thoſe who loveth thee; oh in thee is my reſt, in thee is my peace, in thee is my joy, in thee is my comfort, in thee obtain I bleſſing and happineſs thou art my j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, &amp; the crown of my rejoycing for ever and ever more; Oh wherefore hold me, hold me with thy love thou lovely bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed one, &amp; let me never depart from thee, and then I know thou wilt never depart f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om me, but I ſhall be thine and thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be mine in a perpetual Covenant which never ſhall be broken; oh thou comely beautiful choice one, thy riches is durable, for the glory, the glory, the glory of the Lord thy God is thy dowry for ever more: Unto whom be aſcribed all honour and glory, eternal praiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nown, and everlaſting d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minion for ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmore; ſo be it ſaith my ſoul, and Amen ſaith my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirit; Oh come Lord Jeſus come quickly and take unto thy ſelf thy great pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to reign, for thou art worthy, worthy ſaith my Soul; glory to thee in the higheſt for ever more, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in Edmondsbury com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Goal</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>in the year</hi> 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
